So why is the why is sensuality
dangerous?
Why is wanting pleasure dangerous?
Cuz that's what was said. Understanding gratification.
Understanding gratification.
Delight in the prospect of pleasure.
The danger becomes apparent.
So how else would you describe that
danger? As in why is it dangerous? What's so
What's so
We On the basis of your presently
enduring situation.
Okay. So let's
I want to start with gratification. So right now right now
feeling
a bit unpleasant feeling.
Um So
So
the possibility of
getting rid of that
unpleasant feeling. By
I know like figuring it out or um By
doing something or what?
Doing something or whatever yeah.
So there's there's a pleasure that comes
from that.
But that pleasure is pain.
What you were saying. So the pleasure
Sure. is basically the possibility of
is basically the possibility of
that pain
being taken away.
Yeah. So you
the So the the pain that you're feeling
focusing or giving priority
to the possibility of it disappearing
Yeah. is felt pleasantly. Mhm.
Would you feel any any any any degree of
pleasure on a kind of possibility of pain going
on a kind of possibility of pain going
away if you don't feel pain in the first
place? The pain is primary. The pain is first.
The pain is primary. The pain is first.
Is it? So then the
the extent of pleasure, the greatest
sensual satisfaction the mind fully
gripped relishes in the pain
thing you can experience. Yeah.
is fully determined It's basically so
pleasant because it's painful.
Yeah. So the the greater the prospect of
So the the greater the prospect of
escape and the greater the prospect
would be to a great pain. Mhm.
Uh is then the greater pleasure.
But again, pleasure is not at the end of
that pain. No, it's that It is that. It
is. While you're feeling that pleasure is
While you're feeling that pleasure is
because it's painful and you're feeling
like you're escaping it. That's it.
That's all.
So it's like But if there is no pain
like when the pain disappears, when the
itch disappears, your pleasure goes
flat. So is it like those you know those
pictures where you see
either two faces or a candlestick?
You're basically Oh, yeah. Sure. It's
like Magic eye.
Yeah. Yeah. Whatever. Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. But like it's this It
is the It's both a candlestick and it's
two faces. It's like
It's just different way of looking at
it. You see.
See and you basically two different ways
of looking at it on the right order and
in the wrong order.
Yeah. The wrong order you're prioritizing the
The wrong order you're prioritizing the
pleasure. The right order you're
realizing actually that pleasure is
fully dependent on this pain. Not just
that. That pleasure is this pain.
Okay. Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So, like you could there's still a Yeah.
There is still a degree of separation
when you say pleasure is within the
pain. It's this is this is this. Yet,
you know, you have to express it
somehow. Yeah. But, if you want to be really,
Yeah. But, if you want to be really,
really accurate, uh
that pleasure is the pain. Yeah.
It is also painful.
So, there is no greater pain, that
pleasure would be then seen as painful.
It's all It's all relative, isn't it?
Did you hear that a bit? Sorry, no. If
there is no If there is no greater pain,
There's no greater pain
than this currently presented prospect
of of evading the pain, which is
pleasant. Yeah. That prospect of evading the pain
Yeah. That prospect of evading the pain
would be also seen as unpleasant.
But, the reason why pleasure Why pain is
felt as pleasure when it comes to
sensuality is because it's underlined by
even more pain. Mhm.
If there is no more pain than the uh the
nature of sensuality would be apparent.
It's painful. It always was painful.
That's what Buddha said in the like the
embers, the burning embers, the fire was
always painful.
The only reason it's pleasant is because
it's less painful than your burning
itch. Yes. That's what I mean. It's relative.
Yes. That's what I mean. It's relative.
Well, it's not even relative. It's
painful in itself.
It's relative in your perception of it.
That's what I mean.
Yeah. So, you
Yeah, yeah, yeah. So, nobody Nobody
denies the uh that there is that you can
feel pleasure.
But, what you are feeling pleasant is
the pain.
Yeah. But, but but what I want to say
like so
So, you've got this feeling and you go
this is pleasant.
Not seeing that actually That is That
pleasure there is actually painful. It's
pain, yeah.
And So, see as you just said, not seeing
So, see as you just said, not seeing
that
That's exactly the reason why it's felt
pleasant. Yeah.
Yeah.
So, no perspective on the original pain,
you experience pleasure. And again, it's
like isn't it seems to be more it seems
to be this uh uh
tendency to focus and not see the wider
picture. Mhm. Oh, yeah. Oh, yeah, of
course. Because
you're focusing in on the more
particular pleasure.
Yeah. Not seeing that that's Yeah. fully
enclosed within this pain.
Well, that's why I'll lack That's what
I'm saying.
any opportunity I have, I keep talking
about context. Yeah. Mhm.
You have to learn to see
things that are simultaneously present
that you cannot focus on while you're
focusing on something else.
Which is what I'm
focusing on this. Okay, that's fine.
That is part of the experience. The
other part is that which is there
simultaneously present in the background
that you determine by your focusing.
Which is why this
contemplation or contemplation like this
needs to always be rooted in the
situation as a whole. Otherwise, it
becomes abstract. Yeah.
And um
and you could see if if all you do is
focusing, if all you do is observation
of your nostrils, if all you do is
you know, going come methods and
whatnot, if all you do is look at the
objects of your experience,
how can you then discern
the context of it that you cannot focus
on? Yeah.
Yeah.
Cuz your focus comes from that context.
So, if you cannot discern that, how can
you then see that underlying context of
your current pleasure is pain?
That's right. Yeah, so the context of
the pleasure is pain. Yeah. Yeah, of
course. Which means
Yeah, they're not on the same level.
Yeah. If the pain of the pleasure would
be equally presented with the pleasure
on the same level, it would be obvious,
easy choice for everyone. But the reason
why everybody goes for pleasure is cuz
you don't feel it painful. Oh, okay.
Okay. You have no context on it, in it?
You have no context on it, in it?
In regard to it.
But that's also because
of craving for pleasure.
Which is because of pain
that you have not seen.
As we said, sensuality pressures you
first. Mhm.
That's already pain, through and
through. Yeah, yeah, yeah. And you
cannot escape that situation by any form
of giving in sensuality.
So, the only reason you'll be craving
for pleasure is cuz you don't know the
escape of the arisen pain of sensuality.
So, and that arisen
Sorry, not knowing that escape of the
arisen pressure, it's already your
context of your experience. It's already
peripheral. It's already something you
cannot focus on directly.
As if as Cuz see, focusing works towards
the objects of your senses. Mhm.
But this is the basis for the whole
experience of sense and sense objects.
Mhm. That's where you're already pressured.
That's where you're already pressured.
Yeah. If all you do is focusing on the
sense objects, nostrils, nostrils,
visual, visual, moving, tactile,
if if that's where your mind is at the
at the end of the sense objects,
Mhm. Mhm. how can you then understand
the peripheral context of the whole
thing when you never look in that way?
But how can you How can you focus?
How can you look directly without that
being at the at the pressure Yeah. that
you're experiencing on account of a
pleasant sight?
Where is that pressure to see it?
Where's the pressure you can't see it
like that? Exactly. The pressure is
basically you have been pressured. So,
how can you then know the pressure?
Peripherally. Through the through
through those
anything particular?
Mhm?
That's the necessary basis for What is a
necessary basis? Another necessary basis
for for pressure.
For pressure. How can you know the
Body. Well Yeah, but how can you know pressure
Well Yeah, but how can you know pressure
is there?
Um
As in, you know Because you have
pressure in your body. because of how
you're feeling. Exactly.
Can you directly uh observe with your
senses your feelings?
no. There you go. Yeah.
There you go. Yeah.
So, the whole domain of true feelings,
what it's meant by feelings, pleasure,
um displeasure, neutral, is completely
invisible to those who refuse to give up
the focusing methods.
Yes. It's completely invisible cuz all
you do is look at things and you can't
look at your feeling. You can feel your
feelings. It's like the the the the
mood, the
the
hue, the kind of tone that everything is
kind of already affected by.
Mhm. It's not something that you can It's
It's not something that you can It's
like the weather.
Yeah. You can't look at the weather.
It's just like
Yeah. Yeah. But even even more so um
than the weather,
it's just entirely
the different domain
where observation cannot apply. Yeah.
Yeah. That's what Buddha said, "My teaching is
That's what Buddha said, "My teaching is
for the one who knows
how to feel."
Yeah. You need to learn how to feel.
Mhm. Cuz most people, yeah, would just bundle
Cuz most people, yeah, would just bundle
up what they feel with what they observe
and project it all out there and that's
it. Negate it in doing so.
So, people seek gratification. People
experience happiness in the prospect of
of pleasure of the senses,
which is, you know, not necessarily just
a course
um
sexual pleasure or music or food.
Sen- sensual pleasure, sensuality, is on
the domain of anything
that causes you joy or or sadness if you
lose it on account of sense perception.
Mhm. So,
So,
I don't know. Somebody chopping up the
favorite tree in front of your cottage
and it now exposes the the view to the
road. Uh you get upset when they come to that.
Uh you get upset when they come to that.
You're upset when they come to
sensuality. Mhm.
Yeah. Um um wanting visitors turn up
Um um wanting visitors turn up
want to talk to you.
You get upset.
That's when it comes to sensuality. Mhm.
Want to visitors don't turn up. You get
upset. It's the kind of sensuality. Mhm.
It's the kind of sensuality. Mhm.
It's an account to the experience of the
senses. Yeah. So that's how deep it
goes. It's not just saying no to particular
It's not just saying no to particular
pleasures. Obviously, you need to first
say no to particular pleasures of
unwholesome nature.
But in order to approach it, if you
approach it, you'll be approaching the
whole domain.
So people turn to this happiness and
gratification because uh
the pressure the pressure is too
unpleasant. The mind is untrained in regard to the
The mind is untrained in regard to the
pressure.
And has no other conceivable means of
escape from that painful pressure than
giving
So I want to So I want to ask them so
then what's the escape?
But then I get to the escape. Exactly.
We're not going to go there yet.
No, but I want to ask you
uh why then
if you
were to free yourself
free yourself
or see the extent of the gratification,
see that
no amount of pleasure
uh you you might derive, you have
derived, you are deriving Yeah. it's
actually painful. That pleasure while it
while it's pleasant, it's actually
painful. Yeah. Yeah.
Uh
why then if somebody is to free
themselves from that they would also
free themselves from aversion and ill
will.
As you said to say. Yeah.
Because it's all about trying to It's
all about mastering the assumption of
being able to master the feelings. So,
there's a
I somebody does something, you become
angry, and so you develop thoughts of
you have thoughts of ill will towards
that person to help you deal with the
anger. It's a kind of a response to
It's a kind of a response to
an arisen unpleasant feeling. Mhm.
So, um So, you you derive some pleasure.
So, in that way is it the same
as a sensual response in regard to the
in- in- in- enticing prospect of
engaging with sense objects for the sake
of pleasure.
Seems to be like the same principle. It is.
It is.
So, it's completely the same principle.
Yeah. And not just that, it's probably about
And not just that, it's probably about
80, maybe even 85%
entirely the same motion.
The only thing that varies is the
object. Yeah, exactly. Whether object is
for your as in um in favor of you or
against you. Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
So, that's the thing.
that's how it starts.
That's the first point. Oh, this is
completely against me or completely for
me. Yeah. But that's actually the last
bit of it.
The whole the whole structure of you
resisting the the presently enduring
feeling that pressures you is the the
whole structure of you craving for the
prospect that
basically in its possibility offers you or maybe I
in its possibility offers you or maybe I
can escape this.
Or maybe I can reduce this, or maybe I
can replace this. That's entirely the
same. Sensuality and ill will, entirely
the same.
That's why often anger mixes up with
sensuality. Yeah. Especially with people's sexuality
Yeah. Especially with people's sexuality
and
and uh like
or or like sadness and other emotions
mix with like comfort eating, and and so
on. Mhm. Right.
Pleasant music. Mhm.
You know, many people say, "Oh, music, I
find it help to deal with my pain." Mhm.
It's the same saying like eating cakes
helps me deal with my pain. Mhm.
It is, yeah. Cuz as the Buddha said,
puthujjana knows only um distraction of
sensual gratification
as the only means as the only mean of of
dealing with pain. To manage to manage
this pain.
And the pain either comes from
Yeah. The pain is either basically
So so one feels pain and is feels a pull
towards sense sense sense
sensual objects, you know, like or um
one experiences pain in response to I
don't know
somebody does something that's
displeasing to you.
Mhm. It's basically a move to overcome that.
It's basically a move to overcome that.
You're again pulled towards the sense
object, which is that person. Yeah.
Yeah.
Or rather pressured. And your your focus
so your focus yes, rather than
recognizing that actually I've already
been pressured by this. I've already been
pressured by this. I've already been
subjected to this
Well, there's this feeling enduring.
there's this feeling enduring.
Mhm.
And that came unbidden. That it it and
that came unbidden. That it it and
the possibility of me
having any mastery over that is Well,
it's already
quite obviously false.
Yeah. Yet here you are acting out of the
Yet here you are acting out of the
possibility of mastering the
circumstances that upset me in the first
place, but if I could truly master them,
if I am the master, I wouldn't have been
upset in the first place.
Or I wouldn't have been provoked
sensually in the first place.
aggressively in terms of ill will in the
first place.
So why then? Why
Why
would then people still give in?
Because they kind of know on a level
Yeah, but you don't haven't seen
that anything
that you can possibly experience
as simply enjoyed on its own. It has the
nature to arise.
Why haven't you seen that?
Well, that's a beginningless. Because
because of its ignorance.
Yeah, but why is ignorance still there?
Ignorance is beginningless, but
ignorance remaining there Yeah, yeah,
yeah. is you know, it's not that you
can't do anything about it.
So why why is there nothing done about
it? Again, don't leave the basis of feeling
Again, don't leave the basis of feeling
that we're talking about. The answer's
there.
Because of being still being pulled.
This This
Sure. Yeah. Exactly.
Exactly. So why are you pulled? Because
Why are you pressured by the feeling?
Or rather, how do you
measure that you are pressured or pulled by the
that you are pressured or pulled by the
feeling?
By the unpleasantness.
Uh
is that what you mean? Well, sort of,
but even more accurately, how do you
know that feeling pressured you?
Or how can feeling pressure you?
Did you bother by it?
Yeah, cuz you act out of it.
Yeah. If you don't act out of it Yeah, yeah,
If you don't act out of it Yeah, yeah,
yeah. it's not pressuring. Pressure's
there, but you are not being pressured.
Yeah. So, your weakness Yeah. isn't
measured by the act of weakness Yeah.
for which you are responsible.
And why then would people give in?
So there is the enduring feeling
Because they can't resist that feeling.
They can't withstand that feeling.
endure it. They can't endure it. So
literally if we boil down everything
we've been saying in the last few talks
regarding this this topic
it all comes down to not knowing how to
allow the risen feeling to endure on its
own. I guess that is its nature.
Yeah. And so whenever you
do anything to withstand
that enduring feeling Yeah. You're you're
enduring feeling Yeah. You're you're
rejecting it.
kind of going against your firm Yes.
You're the pressure. Yeah. And and and not
the pressure. Yeah. And and and not
allowing
the nature of these these feelings to
manifest themselves.
And if you ask yourself, "Why am I not
allowing this?" There is no answer. It's
a completely gratuitous assumption.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
I'm not allowing it cuz I never thought
about it, really.
Yeah. Yeah. So I'm not allowing it cuz
I'm keep ignoring the issue of allowing
it. Mhm. Hence ignorance is the most
fundamental attitude
that keeps us bound.
But you can't just
can you just Well, can you just choose
Okay, right. So from now on I'm going to
allow any feeling to endure? No, cuz you
you've done that now
Yeah. on account of you want to get rid of the
on account of you want to get rid of the
feelings. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
You can't escape it so easily. Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
So you can't make a method out of it.
So all you can do cuz it's always going
to be secondary.
So all all you can do
is with a
with a
know the risen feeling that's enduring.
what I wanted to start with. Well, yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. That's what All I teach
is suffering and freedom from it. All I
teach is what people feel and freedom
from it. My teachings for the one who
knows knows what. He knows how to feel.
Not in a wishy-washy
snow snowflake sense. You know, I feel
like this. No, he knows how to feel like
it. He knows how to not
the feelings be the feelings.
Exactly. How not to interfere Yeah. with
the reason feeling, and he knows how to
endure the endurance of feelings. So, being
the endurance of feelings. So, being
mindful of the feeling that's enduring. that's enduring.
And
I want to say
developing this context
of
I've been subjected to this.
Mhm.
So, that whenever you're seeing
But you don't need to be specifically
developing that context. If that context
presents itself, that's fine.
On the basis of you
allowing feeling to endure for as long
as it wants to endure,
and allowing it to change on a more
particular level while remaining the
same in its fundamental nature.
Uh then might reveal you that context,
but not necessarily. So, you don't need
to go look for it cuz you already have
the necessary context,
which is converging point of feeling
that you're allowing to endure. Mhm. So, you
you allow you you allow the feelings to
endure by understanding
by understanding
Do you have no say in it? That you have
no say in it.
That you can't do anything to affect it.
That's what you know as what he so many
times, suffering is in you craving
in regard regarding how you feel, not in
how you're feeling.
And that is
that is pretty much the necessary basis
for any context or contemplation you
want to develop if you want to do it
rightly. The point of present enduring feeling. But
But
Okay, so but we have the experience of
you know, one falls into the
idea that we do have some mastery over
our feelings
because Oh, really?
Oh, really?
I say we don't fall into it, but
basically you can you
Um
basically every particular
thinks that
they have some mastery over assumes that
they have some mastery over their
feelings. don't. They don't really. I think I
don't. They don't really. I think I
remember even even even like way way
before even sitting this
even sitting this
and even thinking about these things
you kind of everybody knows oh, you
can't control how you feel.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, okay, okay.
But So, you already know you're fully
subjected to how you feel and then you
just pray that the circumstances will
make you feel too bad.
But the thing is that what people do
things in order to change their
feelings. Yeah, that's what I mean. So,
that's what they because they think they
can do that. They wouldn't do otherwise.
Oh, yeah, sure, sure. What I mean. So,
like you go I'll like you said I'm
depressed, I'll eat a nice cake cuz
that'll make me feel good because I can
somehow manage my feelings.
right, right, yeah. Well, no And you
have the cake and it does taste nice.
You have a pleasant feeling. That's what
I was aiming at. So, it I I
it worked. Yeah. I can control my
feelings. No, even that the whole the
whole act of trying to do that it's
because of sadness, it's because of
pain. So, that is your motivation.
Yeah. So, through doing this act you are
carrying on the motivation that you're
trying to escape from.
Yeah, that's right. Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So, you know that it doesn't work. But,
what you don't know is that you don't
even have a say in terms of control when
it comes to your environment.
The appropriation of the senses Mhm. and
sense objects.
Mhm. That's where it takes place. Mhm.
Now, you know you are just subjected to
feelings. But, you don't know that you have no
But, you don't know that you have no
right in claiming that these eyes, ears,
nose, smell, taste, touch, etc. are
yours, either.
Yet, that's what everyone claims is
mine. Mhm. And that's why I think I can
indirectly protect my feelings, control
my feelings. I know I I have absolutely
no saying them arising or ceasing if
they want to go.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. But, I I'm fully
committed to fighting for the
environment that will prevent me from
feeling such and such.
yeah, yeah.
So, that's what I mean. They know you
can't control the feelings. There is no
direct relationship with your feelings.
It's an indirect managing the
And that's the key of ignorance and
undoing the ignorance. Like Like, what
you already know, which is that there is
no direct relationship with my feeling.
I am subjected to it. Yeah. Stop
ignoring it and stop trying to escape by
the means of perception Yeah. from that
necessary basis even for touch attempts
of such escape. Mhm. So, why So, why
are
Why is sensuality
dangerous? Why is sensuality dangerous?
Why is sensuality dangerous?
That's what we That wasn't that way we
were Wasn't that your question earlier?
Maybe.
Why is the gratification dangerous?
Yes, that's what you asked. Mhm. Why is
the gratification dangerous?
The gratification
Because the whole thing is it's in
sensuality. Yeah, yeah. Gratification dangerous
Yeah, yeah. Gratification dangerous
scape it's off the central domain.
But why is the act of
regarding pain as pleasant
dangerous? The act
of regarding pain
as pleasure. Yeah.
What Yeah. The act of feeling pain as
pleasure as in acting out of it. Yeah, yeah. Like
as in acting out of it. Yeah, yeah. Like
it's not your act to feel it like this,
it's your mistake. But
why is acting out of that
dangerous? Yeah, so you have a
uh
sensually enchanting object, prospect of
it
nearby. You can access it if you want.
So that experience is a whole, that that
feeling, underlying feeling of that
prospect that you are now in
is unpleasant.
Because the pleasure that's wanted is
not here.
And why you want that pleasure
is not because the thing is pleasant,
but because the arising of the prospect
is painful.
Mhm. That determines how much you want
pleasure.
Because as we described in the other
talks, if the pleasure were truly
contained in the objects
you wouldn't be able to know it before
you're in touch with the objects.
And you certainly would not be able to
not feel pleasure when you're in touch
with the objects, which also happens.
That the pleasure arises with the
prospect of having that thing.
Yes, because the prospect of having that
thing is painful.
So
following that
Because I've not got it and I want it.
Following that prospect
why is that dangerous?
Because you're reinforcing this wrong
direction. Why is the wrong Why is the wrong
Why is the wrong Why is the wrong
direction wrong?
Because uh because you aren't seeing
uh because you aren't seeing
what's painful as painful. You won't
seeing Why is it risky?
Why is it risky?
Danger, risk.
So
you know, I'm knowing gratification that
danger became apparent, the risk became
apparent as it should to say.
So why is it risky? Because
because actually you have no control
over
the arising of pleasure.
What pleasure? This pain.
This pleasure that you this this this
this possibility of the diminishing of
the pain.
Uh-huh. May not
you you you can't do make that happen no
matter what you do.
Well, no, it is a gratification though.
It does gratify to some extent. Uh-huh.
The burning embers do help leper with
his skin disease.
Uh-huh. So
So
there is no risk there then.
If that would be the sole criteria cuz
there is a degree of gratification. So
that can't be the risk. So what is then
What is the risk in that gratification
that you can get?
Because yeah, from the point of view of
of of pain they just pressured me.
Less pain Yeah. is a form of escape.
pleasure Exactly. It's more It's more
agreeable. It's more desirable.
Cuz it's pleasant. But giving in to that
you contains an inherent danger, risk.
Well, I want to say
I want to say cuz it's cuz it's going to
keep reinforcing. It's going to
reinforce this particular direction.
Oh yes, that that's that happens as a
result of it. But that's not the
apparent risk. Like oh, this result will
happen after I do this. No, there is a
risk in it implied risk before you do
it. That's what risk is. That's what
means something's risky. Oh, this is
risky. Knowing risk, you don't need to
wait for the outcome to see the risk.
Then you don't know the risk before you
do it.
So directly before you do it at a
prospect of doing it, you discern that
there is a risk in doing it.
Okay. So what's the risk of it? So the Buddha
So what's the risk of it? So the Buddha
says this
that these
things are
impermanent, unknowable,
subject to change.
Which things? Feelings? No, um Yes.
Yes.
Let's stay on the level of feelings.
Okay. Cuz that's that's again, if you don't
Cuz that's that's again, if you don't
feel unpleasant when the prospect of
desirable desirable object comes your
way, you wouldn't be pressured to act towards
you wouldn't be pressured to act towards
it.
Yeah, yeah.
So let's not leave that necessary basis
out. So go on.
So go on.
It's impermanent and unknowable.
So this this
um
possibility of pleasure that the
diminishing of
the Okay, which is seen as painful.
Mhm.
Is completely out of my hands.
And
could change at any minute.
Which one? What can change?
The The pleasure, the pain.
But what if it changes the way you want
to change?
And then your desire is gratified.
Yeah, that could happen. Or it could go
the other way.
Why is it risky?
Because it could go the other way.
Exactly. Because it's always a gamble. Yeah.
Because it's always a gamble. Yeah.
Uh-huh. And now, but you know, So, 50/50
gamble, so you have a good chance of
winning. Yeah, but how?
So So
So we actually So So because you're not
in any control over the feelings that
arise, I'm reaching out for some pleasure, and
I'm reaching out for some pleasure, and
it could end up in more pain.
Yeah, sure. That's always a risk of any
project in the world.
But again, that's not a fundamental risk
that would make you not go that way at
all. Cuz as I said, from that point of
view, it's 50/50. Yeah. But when the
Buddha says the danger becomes apparent,
means you cannot go back to sensuality
ever again. And then he gives a simile
like a stone broken in half that cannot
be joined together, like a vomited food
that cannot be desirable, like a
dried-up leaf that cannot become green
again. be because you
be because you
um now see that whether
The danger is this path
Yeah, whatever is Whatever
feeling arises, whether it's painful or
pleasant, that's something that you were subjected
that's something that you were subjected
to, and that in itself is
unpleasant. Yes, that's on the level of you being
Yes, that's on the level of you being
pressured by the arising prospect of
sensuality or something like that. But
even being Even being But hit by
pleasure is something that you were hit
by. Yeah, that's what I'm saying. Yeah,
Yeah, that's what I'm saying. Yeah,
okay.
Hit by the by the prospect of
sensuality, which is regarded as
pleasant. Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, yeah.
So, that's absolutely true.
So these things that kind of
change in a way of like, oh, look, now
opportunity for this great desire
for gratification of it.
Um
That's on That's on the like that that
fundamental that still endures.
So you're affected by that. And while
you're affected by that desire, that's
the only way you'll be acting to fulfill
the desire.
Mhm. If the desire were not unpleasant
If the desire were not unpleasant
in its nature,
you wouldn't be pressured to do
anything. And pressuring to do anything or or
And pressuring to do anything or or
following the pressure to do anything is
where gratification is.
And the Buddha said, "When you
understand that, you understand the
danger. The danger becomes apparent."
The danger becomes apparent."
The danger of your act, not of what
you're subjected to. The danger of
responding to the fact that you were
pressured. Yes.
Why is it dangerous to do that?
Because the fact that you were pressured
by say, let's stick to the example
a central object.
It offers itself. You can have it.
It's unpleasant.
So, you have it to get pleasure from it
and escape from the displeasure of it.
That's in itself.
You have no saying that. You're
subjected to that.
But, it's the act of gratification, it's
the act of seeking that pleasure in
order to escape pain that reveals the
That's the danger in it. Doing Doing it
makes it dangerous. Which means in
itself, these things arising on their
own is just how they are.
It's your way of involving yourself with
them that reveals the danger. It's your
way of going for the going for the going
for the going for the
going for the Yeah.
Following the gratification.
Gratification, okay. Why is that
dangerous?
Do you need help?
I do. So,
So,
being pressured by the central object
that's in front of you. Mhm.
That you can have now.
That's the arisen state of affairs.
That's the arisen experience as a whole.
Mhm. The the the unpleasant feeling of
not having this, the mind grip wanting
it. Thing as a whole has arisen as such.
Thing as a whole has arisen as such.
Yeah.
You having the desire to act
about. acting out of it.
Yeah. You're then responding to
something which has arisen which has I
had no
Yeah, but see that's again how you're
explaining it linearly. Okay. Uh the
point is
can you
act towards it
without implying
that you want that same thing that
you're acting towards? To change.
As in your experience as a whole.
Would you be acting out of the being
pressured by the desire? Could you be
acting out of the being pressured by the desire
out of the being pressured by the desire
without implying I want to change this?
change. I want this
I don't want this situation that. I want
it to be like that. So, even if if there
is a like if you don't practice
restraint, if you're unrestrained
householder or layman Yeah. who lives
like just follows his central pleasures.
Yeah. Say a new object of sensuality
appears. Yeah.
And he knows he'll have it. He is going
for it in a sec.
The experience of his desire that has
been manifested when he became aware of
the object is unpleasant.
Because it's not pleasant enough. Yeah.
From his point of view. This situation
I'm in now is not pleasant enough. It
could be more pleasant if I go if I get
that. Yeah. It's just It's just So, basically,
Yeah. It's just It's just So, basically,
whichever way you take it
fundamentally, you're avoiding pain.
Cuz you want Cuz you want something to
change. You want this to change.
Even if you don't If you know you can't
change it, doesn't mean you you still
want to change.
Yeah. That's the risk.
That's the risk.
Wanting change.
And can you engage? Can you give in? Can
you act out of your desire without
implying you want change?
you want change?
No. Either change of this pleasure
Either change of this pleasure for more
pleasure or change of this pain for less
pain or change of this pleasure with
this pain for complete pleasure.
That's all change.
Yet, it's the change that made you
pressure the pressure doing the first
place. The change
The change
pressured me in the first place.
Yeah. Because what else is arising of desire
Because what else is arising of desire
than change
of circumstances that you were pressured
by?
So, you mean something You mean
something changed?
So, I mean like there was no central
object here.
And now there is. Okay. The change.
So, yeah. Okay. So So, something changed
Yeah. on account of which I now find
that there's this possibility of
pleasure. Can that possibility of
pleasure be acted out of without proving
implicitly wanting more change? No.
No. Yet, the change is the only reason you
Yet, the change is the only reason you
were pressured in the first place. Yes.
Yet, your only means of escaping change
is to approve the change which makes you
more liable to pressure of change.
Yeah, yeah.
So, for a leper with a skin disease,
fire cauterizing his wounds
cauterizing his wounds
is is the only means of escape that he
knows that it's making his wounds even
worse that he needs to cauterize even
more that will make the wounds even
worse that he needs to cauterize more.
So, the danger of gratification
of following the desire is the implicit
approval, implicit appropriation,
implicit appropriation,
implicit basic implicit wanting Mhm.
of change.
Mhm. Yet, it's because of the change
that you have this desire that bothers
you in the first place.
So, you make yourself liable to the risk
by doing it. It's not
See, The things have changed. Things
change on their own. That's fine, but as
I said,
how you know you're pressured by
feelings? Cuz you give in.
If you're not giving in, if you stop
giving in to the pressure of feelings,
you can't say anymore feelings pressure
me. So, the measure of how much you're
pressured is the measure of how much you
acted Yeah. out of feelings. Even mentally.
Yeah. out of feelings. Even mentally.
Even mentally, exactly.
Um
so, can you say that the
the danger is the change?
Uh well, the the the danger is
change. Is like they're basically this
again, you did Like, if you just see
change in things, that's not the danger
that you need that you you won't see
this dangerous.
You need to see that you're
giving in, your approval, your
welcoming, delighting in, being happy on
account of the prospect of satisfying
desire cannot be done without implying change.
cannot be done without implying change.
Without implying So, cannot be done
without making yourself subjected to the
risk of change, which is the greatest
risk. Life changes for death.
Life changes for death.
So, why gain changes for loss?
So, why is change
dangerous? Yeah, so you can ask that
question now. Yeah. So, it's the
gratification reveals the danger because
there is no gratification without
implicit change. Thus, change is
dangerous. Why is change dangerous?
Why is change dangerous?
dangerous? Because
think the idea
So, because change is not this
continuous, things continuously just
change. It's like It's like
No,
yeah, okay, it's not
gone. Basically, it's something
Basically, it's something
Change is completely like
comes from a completely conceivable
direction. I I find that things have
already changed.
I can't It's something that's totally
beyond my power, me. Abrupt.
Yeah. It happens to you. Yeah.
It happens to you. Yeah.
Just as we describe in terms of
feelings. Like even people who know,
people who are not relinquishing
sensuality practicing dhamma, they still
know you can't control feelings. You're
subjected to them. So
Yeah. So you can't So you can't So you
can't look at something change, rather
you just go, "Well, that's that's
changed." Yeah, the change we talk about
is not the change of my observation,
which is fully on like what I want to
do, or some like metaphysical theory.
The change is the change of how you
feel. And you have no saying that.
And you have no saying that.
Okay.
Cuz as I said, you can only understand
gratification if you understand the
pressure. You can only understand the danger if
You can only understand the danger if
you understood gratification, that means
understanding of the pressure. What's
the pressure other than feeling?
Hence, if you still think if a person
still think on the level of oh, this is
one thing one thing change a second
thing second thing, that has nothing to
do with what we are talking about.
That's just the domain of science and
physics, which doesn't have the observer that is
which doesn't have the observer that is
self-aware.
Can you account for feelings in physics
and mathematics? Yeah, there you go.
You cannot account for the dhamma.
Full stop.
You So Yeah, so basically
So change is change on the emotional
level. And that's exactly what the
Buddha said when he asked people
"Oh, so what? Your pleasure your your
self is is is your pleasure?" Says,
"Yes." "Oh, so why don't you Why why why
you then feeling pain sometimes? Why you
sometimes feeling neutral?
Cuz if your feeling is yours as in if
you were in control, it wouldn't change.
It would always be the way you wanted it
to be."
So you are subject to change.
Yeah. Fundamentally at the level of feeling.
Fundamentally at the level of feeling.
The direction Yeah.
The direction where change comes from,
as you said, it's completely
inconceivable to you and that's why it's
risky. Because
Because
if something, if you have absolutely no
idea how
how
can this change and whether it's going
to change in agreeable way or
non-agreeable way and what extent of the
non-agreeable way and what harm of the
non-agreeable way.
Um
if all those things you cannot even
account for in theory
Yeah. Um would you regard it thing as non-risk
Um would you regard it thing as non-risk
free? No, it's not.
It would be extremely risky. That's the
danger. That is the danger. So, seeing
change over there, you don't see the
danger. You need to see the right order
of things for danger to become apparent
as the Buddha said. And the right order
is first you need to understand the
gratification of it.
And to understand the gratification of
it, you have to first of all see through
the fact that you've been pressured.
Yeah. Allow the feeling, the pressures
you feel and you stop trying to get rid
of it through explaining it, through
following a meditation technique,
through trying to to sort of deny it, to
try to say oh well look this body is
made of atoms and sensations, nothing is
real, all form of management of that
which pressures you and the only reason
you're doing it is cuz you're still
pressured. So, you've been pressured, there's a
So, you've been pressured, there's a
feeling, there's gratification.
Gratification already started at the
prospect of changing the feeling that
you don't want.
That's right. Changing pleasure for more
pleasure, changing pain for less pain,
changing neutral for basically
distraction of being aware of it cuz it's unpleasant
of being aware of it cuz it's unpleasant
when you're aware of it. So,
So,
it's inconceivable to give in to desire
without wanting and buying that change.
Yet, it's that change you know saying
that puts you in this position in the
first place.
Hence, you keep yourself bound with that
same cycle of bound in that absolutely
uh like a not even a cycle like a
just a perpetual domain of perpetual
risk. Yeah.
Chaos. Yeah.
And what's the then the like the the the
easiest way to deal with it? Ignore it.
And that's the basically I'm just saying
You're already the the the Yeah, the the
being pride suffering.
Yeah, that's that's the definition of
it.
Being subject to suffering, being prey
to suffering.
Being subject to being subject to
suffering place That's what being subject to
place That's what being subject to
suffering means. Yeah.
Means I don't necessarily need to be
suffering now. I am subject to
suffering. Yeah.
Yeah.
In the nature, in my own nature, I can
be affected by suffering. And the only
way to stop that is to see
the danger involved in
involved in
wanting things to change, to be
otherwise than they are. Yeah.
Can you want things to change
without craving?
No. That's what craving is.
Hence Craving is the root of suffering.
Yeah. No craving, no suffering. Even amidst
No craving, no suffering. Even amidst
the adverse circumstances that would
otherwise make you suffer.
So that's when the danger becomes
apparent. Not the danger of this, the
danger of that, the danger of me
if I want this, that's how I already
make myself liable to that danger.
So restraining yourself in regards to
sensuality prevents some danger, but if
you still want it in your mind, to that
extent you're still liable to suffer.
Yeah.
When things change the way you don't
want them to. Mhm.
As in when your feelings change the way
you don't want them to.
Mhm. So then you realize that even your sense
So then you realize that even your sense
of control
towards perceptions, intentions, and so
on
it's completely secondary
to the fundamental a
to the feeling. Mhm.
That you have no say. Yeah. Thus then
your control is not really your
to change. Yeah. Your control then is
not really your control.
That's the inherent nature of feelings.
They are subject to change. They are of
the nature to change.
Yeah. Nature to be otherwise. But again,
But again,
that's not what the danger is.
The danger isn't
the fact that the danger of the nature
to change. The danger is the
um
is wanting them to change.
Is is is
Is approving. The danger is approving of
change through implicitly approving of
change through giving into a desire.
Okay. So
See, you know change is a problem cuz it
bothers you. You want to get rid of it.
Yet the only means of getting rid of it
is approving the means of change.
Which is the Hence the after discrepancy
and contradiction on a very existential
level. Hence the suffering, the
liability to it. Yeah.
That's what I mean. It's not dangerous
if things change. Yes. It's dangerous
you to use means of change to change
things. Yes.
That's where the danger is cuz you
insert yourself and that's why you
become subject to these things. Try to
change change.
So I don't want change.
And thus I'll change that.
it.
That's it. That's the inherent condensed
principle of centrality basically and
the will.
I don't want this change. So I'll change
it. it. Yeah.
it. Yeah.
Because I don't know anything other than
change. So the this change is not the risk.
So the this change is not the risk.
Outcome of me changing it is not the
risk. Or it's all secondary to the risk. The
Or it's all secondary to the risk. The
risk is the fact that I still approve of
that option.
So to speak. That's where the danger is.
Yeah. And so you're keeping it alive.
Keep yourself bound to it fully. Keep
yourself fully subjected to it.
Like your your your wounds won't heal
cuz you keep burning them. So that's the
thing. leads to the question then, so what is
leads to the question then, so what is
the escape?
What do you think is escape based on
this?
Allowing whatever feeling it is to
endure. So gratification understood reveals the
So gratification understood reveals the
danger
thus the escape is then understood.
Which is to not
make to not
want to change
to change
the enduring feeling. The enduring
feeling. Yeah, but you can't quite choose to not
Yeah, but you can't quite choose to not
want that.
How can you then not want it?
How can you then escape it? If you can't
just make a choice, okay, I don't want
this. Well, you by understanding that
that Yeah, what does that entail?
Understanding the nature of feeling is
that it's
it's not something I can change.
Yeah, but it needs to be more accurate. More pinpoint.
More pinpoint.
So as we establish then So we said
wanting change Yeah.
is the implicit risk of proving of
change through your wanting.
is changed and I want
My situation has changed and I want that
to change.
That's the danger. That's the
contradiction. Yeah. involved in this.
Yeah. involved in this.
What are you escaping from?
The currently enduring feeling.
No, no, no, no, no, sorry. Uh
So what what does the word escape mean,
okay? No, I know what escape means, but what
No, I know what escape means, but what
is it escape from? Suffering.
What suffering?
The suffering on account of the enduring
suffering on account of the enduring
feeling.
The craving.
Right, well, is the craving the enduring
feeling? No, no.
No, it's your response to the enduring
feeling. So, that's where suffering is.
Yeah. Not on the level of enduring feeling.
Not on the level of enduring feeling.
Yeah.
So, then why you need to allow the
enduring feeling to be in order to
escape it? It's the allow It's the
allowing, the not fighting, the not But,
what if you allow it for the purpose of
Then you're Then you're Okay, then then
you're still bound up with That's
craving. Then you're not basically doing it on
Then you're not basically doing it on
the right level, yeah. Yeah, then you
crave That's what needs to be drilled and
That's what needs to be drilled and
drilled and drilled.
But, then escape It's escape of
suffering. Escape from the risk.
Yeah. Escape Escape from that danger. Escape
Escape Escape from that danger. Escape
from the danger, yeah.
So, how do you escape Mhm.
wanting to change?
So, hold on, let me phrase it like this,
then. How do you then escape
the danger that is solely
fully always, completely implicit only
when you choose to act this way?
As I said, there is no danger in change
of random things.
There's danger when you imply change for
the sake of change that you are
subjected to.
So, your implication, your craving, your
wanting to change and that's where
danger is.
Yeah. Not in the things. Not in the
things. It's in your It's in your
attitude. So, how do you How do you Like
Okay, let me put it like this. Can you
want Can you have a desire?
Can you act towards
sense object that's unpleasantly
pressuring you Yeah.
without wanting it?
No. Can you want it
Can you want it
without regarding it as pleasurable?
No. So,
So,
if you then
don't regard it as pleasurable,
how can you regard it?
Not want it. Or, how can you regard it
as unpleasurable?
Let's put it like that. By seeing danger
now. Exactly.
So by seeing the danger in it, you turn
away from it. You stop finding it
pleasant. You see that thing as
unpleasant. You find it pleasurable.
Do you want this pleasure? No. Can you
want this pleasure? No. So that's the
escape. There's no There's no steps you need to
There's no There's no steps you need to
do. Yeah, the danger is the escape. Just
have to clarify the identification which
will reveal the danger which will make
this escape possible. Yeah, yeah, yeah,
yeah, yeah.
Same with Four Noble Truths, by the way.
It's not like one, two, three, four.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
It's one within the other. Just
different aspects of the same thing.
So that's the escape of not wanting that
which you used to want.
And seeing
sense Without sense sense desires, the
things that you that you want that you
that you that you saw as a
as a possibility for pleasure Have to be
careful there.
Not objects of your senses cuz now
people will go around saying like oh
that's danger. No, it's not. Yeah, yeah,
yeah, yeah. It's you standing at it in
the first place. It's you regard so
first What What you regard What you
regarded as a possibility for pleasure
you now see as the as it says in the
sutras as the charcoal pit. You see that
thing is no longer seen as
desirable as enticing. It's now seen as
dangerous. even more accurately, it's the same
even more accurately, it's the same
charcoal pit you used to use to burn
your uh
uh
your wounds but your attitude towards
it. that you were deriving pleasure from.
that you were deriving pleasure from.
It's the same charcoal pit that's now
extremely painful cuz your wounds have
healed. Mhm. And actually in that same
sutra the Buddha says that. What if that
man that's now healed gets grabbed by
the two stronger men and they want to
take him back to the fire and drop drop
him in He'd be everywhere kicking and
screaming. Yeah.
So it's not like to go around oh so
sense objects are painful. No, that's
already You already missed Yeah, yeah,
yeah. missed the right basis of seeing
that. Yeah.
What is painful is you already engaging
with sense objects. Whether you approve
or disapprove of them doesn't matter.
That's what I was explaining like most
people do their asubha quite wrongly.
They try to use asubha perception to
replace the perception of attraction.
the perception of attraction.
You discern asubha within it. And sure,
corpses, dead bodies, things like that
can show you that sign. Sign is always
peripheral to what you're looking at.
That's the definition of the sign, by
the way, even in colloquial terms.
Don't walk on grass. You're staring at
the board. You're not staring at the
command of people not walking on the
grass. That's implicit in the letters on
the board. That's the object of your
perception. The sign is in your mind.
So, that's what I mean when there is
the pull towards sense object or
aversion towards sense object, you need
to discern what the what the sign, the
context of it.
And you realize that whether I approve
or disapprove of it, I don't question
the fact that I wanted to kind of get
rid of the pressure that it exerts over
me.
So, I don't question the fact that I
imply desirable change. Yet, it's
because of change that I suffer in the
first place.
So, that's where the danger is.
Hence, the sensory strength and virtue
and sila must It's absolutely not
negotiable must be thoroughly developed
beforehand cuz there's a slightest leak
down the direction of physical action
and verbal action and so on.
You're not going to see it on the right
level of the right sign
or the right context.
So the danger for somebody who starts
from the point of view of ignorance,
the danger is on the level of
engagement. Positive or negative,
doesn't matter.
I want this, I don't want this, doesn't
matter. You're already focused on this.
Yeah. Why would you be focused on this
unless you're already pressured by it?
Either for wanting more or not wanting
it at all.
Or denying it or fighting it or
your focusing. Stop staring and trying
to find the answer through like a
revelation of your perception.
I look back at the fact that you've
already been pressured.
Not directly.
If you look back, you'll be staring at
that. Yeah, I mean just just like Whatever you
Yeah, I mean just just like Whatever you
looked at, that's fine. This is in the
context of it while you're looking at
it. As in
when there is the experience of
pressure, I'm pressured by somebody said something
I'm pressured by somebody said something
upsetting or I'm pressured by somebody
revealed a prospect to sensual sensual
pleasure. Either way, there is this
pressure on me.
So, the experience of pleasure or
sensual pleasure,
I'm pressured by it.
That sensual object, that possibility
couldn't be there without this pressure.
Exactly. So, now I need to What I need
to do is not go in automatically,
habitually, physically, and just get in
touch with that object.
So, once I restrain, still I still want
it on the level of the mind.
And and now you can start doing the work
we talk about on the level of your mind,
which is where sensuality is.
Mhm. And what you do on the level of the mind
And what you do on the level of the mind
is so you are pressured. There cannot be
any conceivable form of engagement
without the implicit desire to get rid
of the painful pressure. It's just
inconceivable. No amount of pleasure, nothing, no no no
No amount of pleasure, nothing, no no no
end game, no result there over there,
later on in time,
can be anywhere else rooted except in me
not wanting this pressure. Cuz again, if
you were not pressured in the first
place, could you conceive any desire
towards the outcome? Inconceivable.
So that when you realize when you start
realizing that, then you see that there
is absolutely no such thing as the end
gratification that will replace the
pressure. The sole pleasure of gratification is
The sole pleasure of gratification is
because of the presently enduring pain
and the endure throughout that time.
The pain of being pressured. Yeah.
That's not on you, but now you clearly
acting, having desire, not restraining
desire, not understanding desire, that's
on you.
And that's why the risk is on you.
That's where the risk is.
Can you then want anything
even if you're not acting out of
if you know that what you want is
actually extremely extremely dangerous
and deadly and there is absolutely no
basis for pleasure and safety in it? Not
at all.
Not at all.
The danger becomes apparent then.
And now that you don't want it, that's
how you escape it.
Mhm. Cuz that was the only connection,
by the way. These things cannot enter
you. You are the one who enters them.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. That's again the
Buddha said that many times, but in that
particular sutra
it's because people take
that what doesn't belong to them, the
Mara does what he wants, controls them.
They make themselves subject to his
control. What are the things that belong
to Mara not to people and people take
them? Sight. Sound. The eye. Well, the
eye, the the the eye objects, ear, the
So basically the six sense base
and everything else you can get from it
within it corresponding to it.
The eye is not mine. So the eye is not
yours, the nose, the the entire body,
the entire experience as a whole cannot
be yours.
Can you regard it as yours if you don't
want it?
No. Yeah. Can you regard it as yours if
it's seen as painful?
No. Can you regard it as yours if it is
if it's seen as constantly oppressing
you? Not at all. Exactly.
So not seeing it in such and such in all
these manners, that's why you regard it
as yours. Yeah.
You start seeing it, you can't regard it
as yours. Mhm.
That's why you don't need to then choose
this cape. The cape is automatic.
Yeah. Understanding anicca correctly,
Understanding anicca correctly,
understanding dukkha correctly, anatta
is automatic. Mhm.
It's the necessary result of it.
It's not Now I do the anatta. Now I do
the anatta.